Guide to the Foundation for Theological Education in South East Asia Records
Yale University Divinity School Library
Foundation for Theological Education in South East Asia Records
1937-2011
RG 180
Yale University Divinity School Library
16.5
(39 boxes)
This collection includes administrative records of the FTESEA and its predecessor organization, the Board of Founders of Nanking Theological Seminary, dating from 1937 to 2011. It also includes publications of the FTESEA, photographs, financial records, and resources from the ATSSEA (Association of Theological Schools in South-East Asia/ Association for Theological Education in South East Asia). The Foundation for Theological Education in South East Asia supports Christian theological education in Southeast Asia in a variety of ways including grants to institutions and projects, scholarships, consultations, and publications. Funds initially devoted to the work of Nanking Theological Seminary were expanded to theological education institutions outside of China following the closure of China to mission work in 1949. As China has become more open to the West, FTESEA has resumed programs supporting theological education there.
Dong nan Ya shen xue jiao yu ji jin hui
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Deposited by the FTESEA
Biographical / Historical
The Foundation for Theological Education in South East Asia (Dong nan Ya shen xue jiao yu ji jin hui) was established in 1963 as the successor organization to the Board of Founders of Nanking Theological Seminary, which was founded in 1937. The original charter of the Nanking Theological Seminary was amended in 1952 to expand the purposes of the organization to include support of theological education in China and other parts of Asia, but the name of the corporation was not formally changed until 1963. The FTESEA was entrusted with disbursement of the annual interests of the Swope-Wendel Fund, which had been established to support the work of Nanking Theological Seminary. When it became impossible to send funds to China after 1949, legal action was taken to redirect the use of the Fund. The Board of Trustees of the FTESEA is constituted of representatives from mission boards in North America and members at large. The FTESEA has a longstanding relationship with the Board of Global Ministries of the United Methodist Church, the legal custodian of the Swope-Wendel Fund.
Frank T. Cartwright, Secretary for China, Japan, Korea and East Asia of the Board of Foreign Missions of the Methodist Episcopal church, was elected Secretary (later called Executive Secretary) of the Board of Founders of Nanking Theological Seminary in 1937 and served until his retirement in 1961. From the late 1930s until late 1960s the Board of Founders (FTESEA after 1963) had a clerical office in New York, which was used by its Secretary and by Henry Pitney Van Dusen, who served as the president of the Board of Founders, and was the first president of FTESEA, serving from 1952 to 1970.
From 1952 to 1957, C. Stanley Smith served as the Board of Founders' Field Representative in South East Asia, with his office in Bangkok for the first year and then in Singapore. John R. Fleming, a Church of Scotland missionary, was appointed Field Representative in 1957 and the office continued in Singapore. When Frank Cartwright retired in 1961, Fleming was appointed Executive Secretary. The official office of the Board of Founders (FTESEA after 1963) was moved to Singapore and a part-time clerical office continued in New York. When the Association of Theological Schools in South East Asia (ATSSEA) was formed in 1959, Fleming was appointed its Executive Director. When Fleming returned to Scotland in 1967, Kosuke Koyama was apppointed ATSSEA Executive Director and Alan Thomson was appointed FTESEA Executive Director, with their offices in Singapore.
When Alan Thomson returned to the U.S. in 1972, Ivy Chou, from Malaysia, was appointed by the FTESEA and the Theological Education Fund of the World Council of Churches to be the Executive Director of the Joint South East Asia office in Bromiley, England. When Chou retired in 1977, Marvin D. Hoff, Secretary for Operations and Finance in the Reformed Church of America, was appointed Interim FTESEA Executive Director. From 1977 to 1994 Marvin D. Hoff served as part-time Executive Director while continuing his work as administrator and pastor in the Reformed Church in America, and later as president of Western Theological Seminary in Holland, Michigan. He became fulltime director in 1994.
Beginning in the mid 1970s there was considerable discussion regarding the appropriate relationship of the FTESEA with related organizations such as the Association of Theological Schools in Southeast Asia (ATSSEA), the Christian Council of Asia (CCA), and the World Council of Churches' Programme on Theological Education (PTE), which was the successor to the Theological Education Fund. The ATSSEA was formed in 1958 with Stanley Smith as its first director; in 1978 it had a membership of forty institutions.
In 1975, the Joint Regional Planning Commission (JRPC) was established as an experimental joint body of the ATSSEA and the FTESEA, to coordinate the disbursement of grants to member schoolsof ATSSEA. The JRPC was reconstituted as the Resource Commission of the ATSSEA in 1977. It continued to process and recommend funding requests, serving as a regional screening agency for the FTESEA. The FTESEA has also funded requests from other organizations. In the late 1970s ATSSEA changed its name to the Association for Theological Education in South East Asia (ATESEA).
As China became more open to the West, the FTESEA resumed support of theological education there. In 1979 the FTESEA began a program of sending books to build up the library at the Nanjing University Center for the Study of World Religions and Nanjing Theological Seminary. Frank and Ruth Cooley served as temporary part time staff for this project. In 1985 FTESEA initiated support of The Chinese Theological Review, an English language journal translating materials written in Chinese by Chinese and publishing the Nanjing Theological Review in traditional Chinese characters with articles from Nanjing's theological journal.
Marvin D. Hoff retired as Executive Director in December 2006 and was succeeded by H.S. Wilson.
More information about the FTESEA is available in Supporting Asian Christianity's transition from mission to church: a history of the Foundation for Theological Education in South East Asia edited by Samuel C. Pearson (Grand Rapids: Eerdmans Publishing Co., 2010.
Scope and Contents
There are additional archives of the FTESEA at the United Methodist Church archives in Madison, New Jersey.
Series I, Administrative Records, is divided into six subseries representing different eras of FTESEA leadership: a) Legal and predecessor documents; b) John R. Fleming era files; c) Alan Thomson era files; d) Ivy Chou era files; e) Marvin D. Hoff era files; f) H. S. Wilson era files. The first sub-series contains records of the Board of Founders of Nanking Theological Seminary and early legal documents of the Foundation for Theological Education in South East Asia. The administrative records include records of FTESEA meetings, including agendas, minutes, reports, and associated financial records, as well as correspondence and memos of the executive directors. These records provide valuable insight into the reestablishment of the Christian church and theological education in China.
Series II, Financial Records, includes financial records such as audits, tax records, and fund requests. Additional information about grants disbursed and other expenses is present in the annual meeting materials found in Series I. Series III contains photographs of FTESEA-related individuals and events. Series IV includes minutes and handbooks of the Association for Theological Education in South East Asia (previously known as Association of Theological Schools in Southeast Asia) as well as material related to some of its member institutions. Series V includes copies of the publications that the FTESEA has sponsored as well as some related to its partners.
Arrangement
I. Administrative Records, 1937-2010
II. Financial Records, 1980-2009
III. Audio-visual Materials, ca.1974-2010
IV. ATSSEA / ATESEA Resources, 1958-2009
V. Publications, 1956-2010
Religious education -- Asia; Universities and colleges -- Asia; Educators; Dong nan Ya shen xue jiao yu ji jin hui; Jinling shen xue yuan
- Administrative Records, 1937-2010; Series I
  - Legal and predecessor documents
    - Minutes, Board of Founders, Nanking Theological Seminary, 1937-1961 (Box 11, Folder 113-118)
    - Report on visit to theological schools supported by Nanking Theological Seminary, 1958 Aug-Oct (Box 11, Folder 119)
    - Constitution, Board of Founders of NankingTheological Seminary (amended), 1941 (Box 11, Folder 120)
    - Charters, Nanking Theological Seminary, 1938, 1952, 1963 (Box 11, Folder 121)
    - First constitution of FTESEA and predecessor documents, 1964-1968 (Box 11, Folder 122)
    - Re. tax-exempt status of FTESEA, 1974 (Box 11, Folder 123)
  - John R. Fleming era
    - Minutes, reports, correspondence, 1968 (Box 36, Folder 334)
  - Alan Thomson era
    - Minutes, reports, 1969 (Box 36, Folder 335)
    - Minutes, reports, correspondence, 1970-1971 (Box 36, Folder 336)
    - Minutes, reports, correspondence incl. of Paul R. Gregory, FTESEA Vice Chairman; Committee on the Role of FTE, 1972 (Box 36, Folder 337)
  - Ivy Chou era
    - Minutes, reports, correspondence of FTESEA Board; Ivy Chou travel notes, 1972 (Box 36, Folder 338)
    - Minutes, reports, correspondence, 1974-1975 (Box 36, Folder 339)
    - Ivy Chou daybook (i.e, correspondence), 1972 Apr-1973 Dec (Box 8, Folder 87-93)
    - Ivy Chou daybook, 1974 Jan-1976 Dec (Box 9, Folder 94-105)
    - Grants from FTE to theological schools, faculty and other projects, 1968-1976 (Box 6, Folder 74)
    - Joint Regional Planning Commission (JRPC) correspondence with Ivy Chou, 1974 Jul 31 - 1975 May 13 (Box 6, Folder 75)
    - JRPC correspondence with Ivy Chou, 1975 May 15 - 1975 Dec 18 (Box 6, Folder 76)
    - JRPC minutes, March organizing meeting, and October 1st annual meeting, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 77)
    - JRPC correspondence with Ivy Chou, 1976 (Box 6, Folder 78)
    - JRPC annual meeting minutes and grants, 1976 (Box 6, Folder 79)
  - Marvin D. Hoff era
    - Meetings / committees / reports
      - Annual meeting minutes, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Executive Committee minutes and correspondence, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Annual meeting minutes, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Membership lists, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - Executive Committee minutes and related materials. Includes document on staffing the FTE, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Agenda and related materials, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Annual meeting minutes, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Executive Committee minutes and related materials, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Resource Commission, correspondence and minutes, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Annual meeting agenda and related materials, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Annual meeting minutes, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Executive Committee minutes and treasurer's report, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Mailing from Marvin Hoff, 1979 Aug 16 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - Correspondence with ATSSEA, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Annual meeting agenda and related materials, incl. proposed new Constitution for FTESEA, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - Annual meeting minutes, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      - Executive Committee minutes and related materials, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 17)
      - Annual meeting agenda and related materials, incl. amended Constitution of FTESEA, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 18)
      - Annual meeting minutes; Special Report on the Church in China by Wendell Karsen, "A New Chapter in Acts", 1980 (Box 2, Folder 19)
      - Executive Committee minutes and correspondence, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 20)
      - Annual meeting agenda and related materials, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 21)
      - Annual meeting minutes, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 22)
      - Executive Committee minutes and correspondence; Document delineating history of the Wendel-Swope bequest, relationship of FTESEA to Board of Global Ministries and Nanjing Theological Seminary, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 23)
      - Annual meeting agenda and related materials, correspondence, minutes, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 24)
      - Annual meeting minutes, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 25)
      - Executive Committee minutes and correspondence, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 26)
      - Annual meeting agenda and related materials, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 27)
      - Annual meeting minutes, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 28)
      - Report on trip to China, Marvin Hoff, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 29)
      - Executive Committee minutes and agendas, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 30)
      - Correspondence, annual meeting agenda and related materials, incl. agreements re. Swope/Wendel Fund, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 31)
      - Annual meeting minutes, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 32)
      - Executive Committee minutes and correspondence, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 33)
      - Annual meeting agenda and related materials, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 34)
      - Annual meeting minutes, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 35)
      - Reports and journals from Nanjing 1986 (Box 3, Folder 36)
      - Executive Committee minutes and requests for funding, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 37)
      - Annual meeting agenda, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 38)
      - Annual meeting minutes, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 39)
      - China/Canada/U.S. program correspondence, 1987 May (Box 3, Folder 40)
      - Executive Committee minutes and requests for funding, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 41)
      - Annual meeting agenda, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 42)
      - Annual meeting minutes, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 43)
      - Executive Committee minutes and requests for funding, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 44)
      - Annual Meeting agenda and minutes, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 45)
      - Executive Committee minutes and correspondence, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 46)
      - Mailing to FTE board re Zhao Zhilian, Alan Thomson, Tiananmen Square, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 47)
      - Annual meeting agenda and related materials, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 48)
      - Annual meeting minutes, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 49)
      - Executive Committee minutes and correspondence, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 50)
      - Mailings to FTE board re Bossey, reports on theological ed., 1990 (Box 4, Folder 51)
      - Annual meeting agenda and related materials, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 52)
      - Annual meeting minutes, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 53)
      - Mailings to FTE board re China Christian Council, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 54)
      - Executive Committee correspondence, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 55)
      - Executive Committee minutes, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 56)
      - Executive Committee minutes and correspondence, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 57)
      - Annual meeting agenda, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 58)
      - Annual meeting minutes, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 59)
      - Executive Committee minutes, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 60)
      - Annual meeting agenda and related materials, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 61)
      - Annual meeting minutes, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 62)
      - Special meeting 10/12/94 and related minutes, incl. Executive Committee special meeting 9/8/94, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 63)
      - Presentation by FTE to Resource Commission, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 64)
      - Executive Committee minutes, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 65)
      - Annual meeting agenda and related materials, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 66)
      - Annual meeting minutes, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 67)
      - Report from Marvin Hoff re visit to China, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 68)
      - Executive Committee minutes, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 69)
      - Annual meeting agenda, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 70)
      - Annual meeting minutes, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 71)
      - Corrections to minutes, 1995 (Box 22, Folder 193)
      - Executive Committee mailing and financial report, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 72)
      - Mailing to FTE board, incl articles on Chinese Theological Ed., 1996 (Box 5, Folder 73)
      - Call to annual meeting, agenda items, 1996 (Box 22, Folder 194-195)
      - Annual meeting minutes; Executive Committee minutes, 1996 (Box 21, Folder 166)
      - Report from Marvin Hoff re. visit to China; Call to meeting for Executive Committee, 1997 (Box 21, Folder 167)
      - Agenda and materials for 1997 Dec annual meeting; Minutes of 1997 Aug Executive Committee meeting (Box 21, Folder 168)
      - Call to annual meeting, 1997 (Box 22, Folder 198)
      - Annual meeting minutes; Executive Committee minutes, 1997 (Box 21, Folder 169)
      - Call to annual meeting, 1998 (Box 22, Folder 199)
      - Agenda and materials for 1998 Dec annual meeting (Box 21, Folder 170)
      - Annual meeting minutes; Executive Committee minutes, 1998 (Box 21, Folder 171)
      - Agenda and materials for 1999 Dec annual meeting (Box 21, Folder 172)
      - Annual meeting minutes; Executive Committee minutes, 1999 (Box 21, Folder 173)
      - Documents on China, 2000 Jun (Box 21, Folder 174)
      - Call to mission / vision retreat, 2000 Jun (Box 22, Folder 200)
      - Documents for retreat, 2000 Sep (Box 21, Folder 175)
      - Directory, 2000 (Box 22, Folder 201)
      - Call to annual meeting, minutes, 2000 (Box 22, Folder 202-205)
      - Agenda and materials for 2000 Dec annual meeting (Box 21, Folder 176)
      - Annual meeting minutes; Executive Committee minutes; FTESEA Directory, 2000 (Box 21, Folder 177)
      - Proposal from auditing firm, 2001 Jan (Box 22, Folder 206)
      - Minutes of special meeting, 2001 May 2 (Box 21, Folder 178)
      - Minutes of 2001 Sep Executive Committee meeting; Call to December meetings (Box 21, Folder 179)
      - Annual meeting minutes; Executive Committee minutes, 2001 (Box 21, Folder 180)
      - Meeting documents, 2001 (Box 22, Folder 207-210)
      - Documents on China for participants in North American Ecumenical Roundtable on China, 2002 (Box 22, Folder 211)
      - Agenda and materials for 2002 Dec meeting (Box 21, Folder 181)
      - Annual meeting minutes; Executive Committee minutes; FTESEA Directory, 2002 (Box 21, Folder 182)
      - Minutes of 2003 Oct Executive Committee meeting; report of Marvin Hoff on trip to Asia (Box 21, Folder 183)
      - Documents for 2003 Dec Executive Committee meeting (Box 21, Folder 184)
      - Agenda and materials for 2003 Dec meeting (Box 21, Folder 185)
      - Annual meeting minutes, 2003 (Box 21, Folder 186)
      - Meeting documents, 2003 (Box 22, Folder 212-217)
      - Call to 2004 Dec meetings; Report on Sixth Symposium on Church Ministry in China (Box 21, Folder 187)
      - Report on Exhibition of Bible Ministry of the Church of Christ in China, 2004 (Box 21, Folder 188)
      - Minutes of Executive (Search) Committee meetings (also Box 23, folder 222), 2004 (Box 21, Folder 189)
      - Executive Committee and annual meetings, 2004 (Box 23, Folder 218-225)
      - Re. search process for new Executive Director, 2005 Feb (Box 23, Folder 226)
      - Report on forum on China's new religious regulations, 2005 Mar (Box 23, Folder 227)
      - Executive Committee meetings, 2005 Apr, May (Box 23, Folder 228-230)
      - Report on Hoff trip to China, 2005 Jun-Jul (Box 23, Folder 231)
      - Call to meetings, Executive Committee agenda, 2005 Dec (Box 23, Folder 232-233)
      - Executive Committee and annual meeting minutes, Board Executive Session minutes, reports, directory, 2005 Dec (Box 24, Folder 234-236)
      - Report on trip to China of Gerald Anderson, Marvin Hoff, and Ben Chan for funeral and memorial service of Dr. Wenzao Han, 2006 Feb (Box 24, Folder 237)
      - FTE Board Executive Session, Terms and Conditions for FTESEA Contract with Dr. Henry S. Wilson, 2006 Apr (Box 24, Folder 238)
      - Agenda,documents, minutes for Executive Committee meeting, incl. chronology of legal actions regarding FTESEA, 2006 Apr (Box 24, Folder 239)
      - Mailing of Marvin Hoff to Member Schools of ATESEA, 2006 May (Box 24, Folder 240)
      - Memo from Marvin Hoff, draft report fo Nominations Committee, 2006 Oct (Box 24, Folder 241)
      - Executive Committee meeting for orientation of new Executive Director, 2006 Oct (Box 24, Folder 241a)
      - Agenda,documents, minutes for Executive Committee meeting, 2006 Dec (Box 24, Folder 242)
      - Annual meeting, program for retirement banquet honoring Marvin and Joan Hoff, 2006 Dec (Box 24, Folder 243)
    - Correspondence
      - Correspondence of Marvin Hoff, 1976-1994 (Box 25, Folder 246-254)
      - Correspondence of Marvin Hoff, 1995-1999 (Box 26, Folder 255-262)
      - Correspondence of Marvin Hoff, 2000-2001 Jun (Box 27, Folder 263-271)
      - Correspondence of Marvin Hoff, 2001 Jul - 2002 Mar (Box 28, Folder 272-279)
      - Correspondence of Marvin Hoff, 2002 Apr-2003 Jul (Box 29, Folder 280)
      - Correspondence of Marvin Hoff, 2003 Aug-2004 Jul (Box 30, Folder 281)
      - Correspondence and documents re. Swope-Wendel Fund, 1982-1995, n.d. (Box 36, Folder 340)
    - Program documentation
      - China Libraries project
        - Correspondence between Frank Cooley and Zhao Fushan, 1979 Dec - 1980 Apr (Box 10, Folder 106)
        - Nanjing correspondence, 1979-1981 (Box 10, Folder 107)
        - Reports and updates, 1980, Feb-Mar (Box 10, Folder 108)
        - Purchase orders for books from Baker and Taylor, 1980 (Box 10, Folder 109)
        - Correspondence re pastor's libraries, 1980-81 (Box 10, Folder 110)
        - Bibliographies sent to Nanjing, 1981 Mar 6 (Box 10, Folder 111)
        - Book lists sent to Nanjing, Feb 1982 (Box 10, Folder 112)
      - Grants
        - JRPC annual meeting minutes and grants, 1977 (Box 7, Folder 80)
        - JRPC correspondence, 1977 (Box 7, Folder 81)
        - Grant requests to FTE, 1978 (Box 7, Folder 82)
        - Grant requests to Resource Commission, 1979-1980 (Box 7, Folder 83)
        - Resource Commission meeting minutes, October 24-26, 1980 Oct 24-26 (Box 7, Folder 84)
        - Grants from Resource Commission, 1980 (Box 7, Folder 85)
        - Grants from Resource Commission, 1981-1982 (Box 7, Folder 86)
    - Addendum
      - Regarding scholarships for Asian students, 1987-1997 (Box 39, Folder 1)
      - Report of FTESEA/ATESEA Lectures, Indonesia - Letty M. Russell and J. Shannon Clarkson, 2004 March (Box 39, Folder 2)
      - Report by Andrew K. H. Hsiao: "The Rewakening of the Church in China", 1979 (Box 39, Folder 3)
      - Marvin Hoff trip to South Africa, 2000 (Box 39, Folder 4)
      - Correspondence and agreement re. FTESEA archives being hosted by Yale Divinity Library, 2000-2002 (Box 39, Folder 5)
      - Executive Director reports, annotated, 1999-2001, 2004 (Box 39, Folder 6)
      - Executive Director correspondence and documents, 1997-2007 (Box 39, Folder 7-8)
      - Contracts between Marvin Hoff and FTESEA, 1983-2005 (Box 39, Folder 9)
      - Correspondence, proposals re. work in Mekong Region / Indochina, 2000, no date (Box 39, Folder 10)
      - Report of Executive Director of ATSSEA and Dean of the SEAGST to the Executive Committee meeting, Taiwan by Emerito P. Nacpil, 1975 (Box 39, Folder 11)
      - Correspondence and documents related to Nominations Committee, 1983-2001 (Box 39, Folder 12)
      - Duplicate financial records, annotated, 1978-2006 (Box 39, Folder 13-14)
  - H. S. Wilson era
    - Contracts between FTESEA and Dr. H. S. Wilson and related documents, 2006, 2010 (Box 38, Folder 350)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence, directory, 2006-2009 (Box 38, Folder 351)
    - Executive Committee meeting agenda, documents, minutes, 2007 Jun (Box 38, Folder 352)
    - Executive Committee meeting, annual meeting, 2007 Dec (Box 38, Folder 353)
    - Executive Committee meeting, 2008 Jun (Box 38, Folder 354)